let's move now to implicit threading implicit
threading is something that is getting more
and more popular this has been happening since
years now it is not really something new and
it's basically about simplifying even further
the life of programmers when it comes to multithreaded
processes the idea is to let the compiler
create code to handle threads so that the
overhead or the extra work needed by the programmer
is saying things like "create a thread" "destroy
a thread" "run this function with a thread"
gets even lower than the one I presented
with the code before we are going to look
at two ways / two mechanisms that exist one
is the concept of thread pool and the other
is OpenMP thread pools is something that is
used quite a lot the idea is that instead
of creating a thread when you need it you
create a set of threads a pool of threads
at the beginning so that first of all you
don't pay the price of creating a thread when
you need it because when you need a thread
you might want to do something rapidly and
creating the thread at that time would affect
the response time or latency whatever
you want as a metric because you have to create
a thread at that moment so you can create
the threads at the beginning of the execution
and just keep them in a pool and then whenever
you have to run something in a thread you
pick one of the free threads in the pool and
you make it run a certain function of course
you can play a bit with the pool size to decide
what is the maximum parallelism degree and
you have mechanisms so that if all the threads
in the pool are already taken you can even
decide to create more threads or just ask
the one that wants the thread to do something
to actually wait because all available ones
are taken and in practice this might be also
good because you know that at the end of the
day you have a fixed number of physical cores
and since each physical core can only run
one thread at the time having too many threads
depending of course on what kind of operations
they are doing especially if they are CPU-bounded
(we will see this in the next lecture , simply
put if they do a lot of computation and they
are not really requesting a lot of input/ouput from
the operating system and the hardware) having
too many threads does not really help an alternative
is OpenMP an extra mechanism for implicit
threading is OpenMP the idea is that you actually
use directives for the compiler so that when
you compile your code the compiler automatically
adds all the parts that are related to creating
threads assigning functions to them and so
on so basically just look at this example
here you see you put this directive for the
compiler and what you are telling the compiler
is everything that happens all the functions
and lines of code you have in between these
brackets they should be run in parallel and
you should create one thread per core that
is available in my computer when you compile
this then the compiler will add all the extra
lines needed to create a thread destroy the
thread join the thread at the end to make
sure the main thread doesn't proceed before
this is done and so on so basically if you
try to do this and then you run the program
you will get n times this print where n is
the number of cores you have in your machine